Prediction markets, the platforms for
betting on
virtually anything. Who wins the next
NHL game? How many tweets will Elon Musk
post in April? Will Bitcoin be up in the
next 5 minutes? Can Iran and the US
reach a nuclear deal? Are aliens real?
Will Taylor Swift become pregnant before
marriage? And will Jesus return before
2027? All things you can gamble
I mean, trade on via platforms like
Kalshi, the largest prediction market in
the US, and Polymarket, the largest such
platform globally. Legally ambiguous and
outright outlawed in a number of
advanced economies, prediction markets
have been absolutely thriving in the
United States, all thanks to a legal
technicality.
Prediction markets, for some reason,
don't count as gambling. Something that
puts jurisdiction for the platforms
under the federal CFTC rather than state
gambling laws. And everyone is rushing
to take advantage. Financial and
gambling platforms alike are launching
their own offerings, traditional
exchanges are investing in the space,
CNN, Fox, CNBC, Google, the MLB, UFC
have all announced partnerships. Even
Trump has announced plans to launch his
own prediction market. And it's easy to
see why there's been such a gold rush.
With the industry turning the CEOs of
Polymarket and Kalshi and Kalshi's
co-founder into some of the youngest
self-made billionaires. Now, to many,
these platforms amount to little more
than glorified casinos. But founders
will argue that they're much more than
that. That they offer valuable
prediction data and news information. A
way for governments, corporations, and
individuals to hedge against risks. Or a
method for users to trade off their
unique expertise to get ahead
financially. Things that are all argued
to make prediction markets a net good
for society.
But what if the way these prediction
markets advertise themselves went
against all of that?
What if most users actually lost money
on these platforms?
>> Kalshi lets you legally trade on
anything.
>> What if prediction markets were prone to
abuse?
>> How many hurricanes do you think we'll
HAVE THIS YEAR?
>> WHAT if ads specifically targeted
younger users to get them hooked with
promises of big winnings?
>> We're in Florida asking people WHAT THEY
PUT THEIR MONEY ON.
>> WOULD ALL OF THAT STILL be a net good?
Well, that's what we're going to cover
in today's video. We've seen a lot of
recent updates and research come out on
prediction markets that I think warrants
discussion. But, before we get into any
of that, for those who may not have been
following this whole kerfuffle, let's
start at the beginning.
How did we get here?
Prediction markets are platforms that
allow users to bet on the outcome of
virtually any future event. Users can
find a market that they want to bet on,
buy a contract according to how they
want to bet, sometimes represented by a
blockchain token depending on the
platform, for a price that's based on
the odds of that event occurring that
way, and then either hold the contract
until the event is triggered and a
payout is made, or sell the contract to
another user earlier with the price of
the contracts changing based on the
evolving odds of that event. If you
hold, however, the result is binary.
Either the contract hits and you earn a
predetermined return based on your entry
price, or it doesn't and you lose it
all. Platforms like Kalshi and
Polymarket charge a small fee on each
transaction that can range anywhere from
a few basis points to over 3% based on
the odds of the contract, but they
otherwise don't partake in the bet
themselves. That distinction's important
because while traditional bookmakers
often take the other side of each bet
with favored odds, prediction markets
argue that they are merely facilitating
bets and act more as a derivatives
exchange. You see, these types of
contracts, known as event contracts, are
nothing new. The North American
Derivatives Exchange, formerly Head
Street Inc., has been trading event
contracts, which are technically a type
of swap and sometimes referred to as
binary options because of their all or
nothing outcome, since 2004.
But, the events that these contracts
cover is what's really changed here.
Historically, the CFTC, the Commodity
Futures Trading Commission, has been
very restrictive in limiting what type
of events these contracts can be on. In
fact, back in 2012, they blocked the
Nadex from listing their own elections
event contracts, deeming them a form of
gaming, something explicitly prohibited
under the Commodity Exchange Act. Even
the Iowa Electronic Market, which has
been permitted to trade election
contracts for a number of decades, was
only allowed to operate under strict
research-focused, non-commercial
conditions. And so, originally, Kalshi
was actually blocked, too, when it tried
listing event contracts on congressional
control in 2023. This time around,
however, Kalshi sued, and a judge
actually ruled in the platform's favor,
arguing that elections didn't constitute
gaming, and that the CFTC's judgment on
public interest wasn't authorized by
Congress. And so, the floodgates opened,
with elections betting quickly sweeping
across the country. But here, you might
be drawing a few question marks, given
that these platforms today have pushed
heavily into sports betting, which, by
some definitions, is a form of gaming.
So, as you'd expect, there's been a lot
of legal pushback, with a number of
states angry that they are missing out
on gambling tax revenue, and that these
platforms should fall under their state
gambling laws. But, under the new
Trump-appointed head of the CFTC,
Michael Selig, the institution has not
only allowed this activity for,
some reason,
it's vehemently defended it, with the
group issuing public messages purporting
the value of these platforms and arguing
that the CFTC has sole jurisdiction over
these markets.
>> To those who seek to challenge authority
in this space,
let me be clear.
We will see you in court.
>> And the institution has made true on
that promise, with the CFTC suing states
for restricting prediction market
activity, filing an amicus brief in
support of crypto.com in its dispute
with the Nevada Gaming Control Board,
and even getting a judge to temporarily
drop criminal charges brought on by
Arizona. With the institution completely
abandoning the appeal it originally
filed against Kalshi's original
elections contracts. And so that's how
we find ourselves today with our markets
on whether Justin Trudeau and Katy Perry
will break up by August. Now, there do
remain some limits on what these
contracts can involve. The CEA may
explicitly outlaws contracts with
references to terrorism, assassination,
war, and unlawful activities. But
outside the CFTC just blindly ignoring
the gaming restrictions, even some of
those contracts are pretty easy to
access thanks to some markets, namely
Polymarket's main offering, operating
offshore. Meaning savvy users can still
largely access these types of bets. But
this is where executives will defend
these platforms. Well, most people again
view prediction markets as just the
latest degenerate iteration of
investment gamification, advocates,
including the CFTC I guess, will argue
that they're much more than just
gambling platforms. They're presented
for one as an innovative way to hedge
risks. Companies, for example, can
mitigate against an unfavorable
candidate winning an election by betting
accordingly. And even for sports, team
managers can bet in way that mitigates
the downside of a loss for their team.
Then there's the data, that sweet sweet
forecasting data that prediction markets
have become famous for. You see,
prediction markets tap into the
so-called wisdom of the crowds. The idea
that collectively society's estimates
are more accurate than those of
individual experts. It's It's similar to
the efficient market hypothesis for
stock markets. If markets have a lot of
participants and low friction, then the
markets collective buying and selling
activity should roughly bring the price
of things close to their true intrinsic
value, especially as experts take
advantage of any mispricings and
arbitrage opportunities and themselves
contribute to the price discovery for
that thing. So with prediction markets,
the idea goes that if people are allowed
to bet on it, the probabilities that
surface from the trading activity on the
platforms will reflect fairly accurate
forecasts. And there is some truth to
that. Polymarket gained massive
publicity in the 2024 US presidential
election for showing Trump as the winner
weeks before professional polls did.
Even the Iowa Electronic Market
demonstrated back in the '90s the power
of market-based forecasts.
>> In comparison to more than 900 polls
over the last two decades, the IEM has
been closer to the actual outcome 74% of
the time.
>> With the key argument being that bettors
aren't influenced by the same bias that
might sway news outlets or polls. It's
also why many executives have argued
that we should try and financialize
everything because if we have people
trading on it, then we'll have a pretty
good idea of where it's going to go in
the future. With the Polymarket CEO even
arguing that regarding war contracts,
people in the Middle East can use
prediction markets to decide quote,
"Whether we sleep near the bomb
shelter." Now, just shoving our ethics
to the side here for a sec, if you
squint your eyes just right, you can see
the argument. And for individuals,
prediction markets are presented as a
way to grow your money. Traditional
investments are plagued with corruption,
but with prediction markets, the layman
can profit from their niche expertise or
unique insight, which for anyone who's
previously been unable to monetize their
180 hours of counting the cars that pass
through a certain intersection,
probably sounds like a dream come true.
Except that's not really what we see for
most people.
When it comes to how much money users
actually make from prediction markets,
the odds aren't much better than what we
see for things like day trading, where
the vast majority of people lose money.
One recent analysis by Jordan Bender,
managing director of gaming equity
research with Citizens, found that the
median ROI for retail users of
prediction markets was negative 8% from
July 2025 to March 2026. In a separate
independent blockchain analysis of
Polymarket by Andre Sergankov, found
that 84% of Polymarket users have
realized losses, with just 2% of the 2.5
million participants having made more
than $1,000
over their trading history. So, you can
see that despite how prediction markets
are presented, making money with them is
unlikely for most. In fact, the median
ROI from the Citizens note was worse
than the median for legal US sports
betting, which sat at negative 5%. Now,
there are of course examples of people
who have profited from their niche
experience, especially in the earlier
days of the markets, when there was less
competition. And there is some evidence
that select subsets are able to achieve
better returns. The Citizens analysis
found that users trading over $500,000
saw their ROI improve to 2.6%. But for
anyone who's trading just a few thousand
dollars or less, i.e. most of the people
the platform advertises to, the average
returns are all negative, which seems to
align with the idea that the markets'
returns are largely captured by a small
cohort of professional users, i.e. those
who exploit arbitrage opportunities
between platforms, market making
institutions, or groups with the
infrastructure to execute on
opportunities faster than others. And
while prediction markets argue that they
are for more than just sports gambling,
that's still their bread and butter,
where the vast majority of their
revenues come from. Kalshi, for example,
holds a 90% share of the US prediction
market and sees a growing $13 billion
in monthly volume. Roughly 79% of this
is strictly for sports betting.
The second largest category behind it,
crypto, which takes up 2/3 of non-sports
betting categories, something we
already have markets for. Now, beyond
the concerns around the actual
experience users have on these
platforms, there's also the issue of how
people abuse these prediction markets
and what that means for other users. For
one, there's the insider trading. In
financial markets, it's illegal to trade
securities on information that's not
otherwise available to the public, since
doing so erodes trust in said markets.
It's why insiders are traditionally
required to publicly disclose their
trades and their positions. But, as
you'd expect from a platform that lets
people bet on
literally anything, people have been
quick to abuse their privileged
information on
literally whatever. Polymarket, for
example, saw a number of users make
substantial bets around the war in Iran
and America's military actions in
Venezuela days and even hours before
they occurred. In fact, just this week,
an NPR analysis discovered a trader who
had made $300,000
betting on Joe Biden pardons, bets that
for some were rapidly approaching 0%
odds. There's also the risk of market
manipulation given how trivial some of
these markets are. There are bets on
whether YouTuber Moist Critical will get
a haircut or what color Trump's tie will
be during the State of the Union
address. And there have been numerous
accusations of people unfairly
influencing the outcome of these
markets.
>> Lord Miles is sending money to the same
address which is betting against him.
>> This is something Trevor Noah even poked
fun of at the Grammy Awards.
>> Potato.
If you had me saying potato on
Polymarket, you made a ton of money. It
goes to demonstrate how easily abused
these markets are, even if it was a
joke.
The real contract didn't have the word
potato as an option. Even around more
serious news stories, we've seen
examples of people trying to influence
prediction market outcomes. There have
been examples of journalists threatened
for how they described a missile strike
because of its impact on a $23 million
Polymarket market. And there are Discord
communities allegedly discussing ways to
influence the interpretation of news
stories to help settle their online
bets. Now, prediction market operators
do have the power to veto bets and ban
users.
But they've been slow to enact real
changes around these risks. For example,
while both platforms recently announced
changes like preemptively banning
athletes from betting on their own
sport, this only came last month in the
face of proposed legislation to ban
sports prediction markets following a
series of insider trading scandals
around college and professional games.
And these late policy changes make sense
because, in a way,
insider trading is good for these
platforms when it comes to prediction
data. So, it's clearly dangerous to
assume that these platforms will
self-regulate. And while the CFTC is
supposed to be the one policing this
activity and ensuring that insider
trading and market manipulation aren't
running rampant, it hasn't been doing
much to penalize abusers. To date, there
have only been two publicly reported
enforcement actions from the institution
regarding prediction market users. One
against a political candidate for
trading on their own candidacy, and one
against an editor for Mr. Beast for
betting on his videos. Both of which
were actually referred by Kolshi. In
fact, the CFTC has taken more legal
action against states trying to ban
prediction markets than perpetrators of
these legal activities. Not to mention
that regardless of how sophisticated the
tracking measures used by these
platforms might be for finding insiders
and trying to clear them out,
it's just not feasible to accurately
identify insiders and market
manipulators across the slew of markets
available when you allow people to bet
on literally anything.
So, you can see that there are a lot of
problems and risks that users face when
using prediction markets. But,
executives for these companies have
arguments there as well. For one, these
issues are nothing new. Even traditional
markets see insider trading and market
manipulation. And while yes, the
majority of the platform activity is
tied to sports betting, Kalshi CEO Tarek
Mansour has argued that liquidity begets
liquidity. Sports betting might not be
the most useful application of Kalshi
for society's sake, but that activity is
needed to attract other activity for the
more important stuff like economic and
political forecasts. So, while people
may use these markets to speculate just
as some do with stocks and options,
these platforms are ultimately just
another financial exchange. And we've
seen a lot of effort to legitimize that
side of the business, with even FanDuel,
an actual gambling company, scoring a
partnership with CME Group, a
traditional derivatives marketplace, to
set up a prediction market.
Which is all a bit awkward when we get
to how these platforms promote
themselves.
As highlighted, prediction markets have
bent over backwards to argue in the
courts that they are not a casino.
Well, when it comes to how they
advertise, they certainly present
themselves as one. In 2025, during the
NBA finals, Kalshi aired a completely
AI-generated ad that feels like a
cocaine-induced fever dream, with people
screaming, partying, and of course,
betting their money.
>> Will egg prices go up this month?
>> I think we'll hit $20.
>> Social media ads, meanwhile, showcase
users anxiously watching sports matches
and press releases hoping for their
contracts TO HIT.
>> YES!
MY HERO!
>> WITH OTHERS FLAUNTING the money they're
making.
>> Yo, you have 450 right now? What?
>> Bro, I only use Kalshi now.
>> This despite that not seemingly being
the typical experience. And despite what
CEOs have said about their value beyond
sports betting, a good chunk of their
ads still focus on just that, even
explicitly comparing prediction markets
to traditional sportsbooks. Now, to be
fair, the companies have had efforts to
diversify beyond this activity,
especially because sports betting tends
to be a male-dominated industry. So,
we've also seen a lot of ads targeted at
women. And the advertising there
isn't much better.
>> Do you think Kylie Jenner and Timothy
Chalamet will actually get engaged?
>> There's actually a great article from
The Atlantic that covers exactly this,
discussing how ads will use terms like
girl math, girl boss, and talk about
paying for their coffees with their
prediction market winnings. Meanwhile,
affiliated accounts like Kalshi Culture
and
Polymarket post memes and
influencer-style videos to promote the
platforms. And a number of these ads
really blow out of proportion the upside
here. One that later showed up in a
lawsuit even read, "I was about to be
unable to pay my rent, but I got 2 years
of rent through Kalshi's predictions.
It's amazing." I also have to shout out
Polymarket's just awful social media
presence on X, where the company has
blatantly posted misinformation,
conspiracies, and at times even racial
slurs to draw traffic to its website. A
bit ironic for a company that deems
itself a truth machine. And these are
just the direct marketing campaigns.
There's also, of course, the influencer
marketing that these platforms have
carried out. Paying a slew of
celebrities and online personalities to
promote their offerings. Some focus on
sports, a number try to legitimize the
economic and finance trading aspects.
Others, not so much.
>> You're going to kiss Noah Beck. There's
a 69% chance. It's going Yeah, it's like
it's going up in the market right now.
>> The cherry on top, a good chunk of these
ads forget to disclose that they're paid
promotions. So, maybe they aren't. Maybe
this guy just really likes talking about
sophisticated trading patterns at the
beach.
>> Do you think uh P. Diddy will be
sentenced to life in prison?
>> Oh, hell yeah.
>> And while I wish it stopped there,
Kalshi and Polymarket have made what's
probably a really smart marketing move
and introduced referral programs.
Whereby with Kalshi, users can get $25
for themselves and a referral when their
friend spends the same amount on the
platform. And Polymarket actually
providing a share of trading revenues
from your referrals when you bring them
to the platform if you yourself have
traded at least $10,000 worth of bets on
Polymarket. So, beyond the massive
influencer marketing budgets, we
actually have users incentivized to talk
about how great the platforms are so
that they can help onboard their friends
and family and start making money off of
their betting activity. With some even
utilizing their own social media
accounts and making over-the-top claims
about the upsides without the same
marketing guides to hold back their
messaging.
>> Don't get a job, do this instead.
>> And then, there's the ecosystem built
around prediction markets. The
influencer courses, tools, platforms,
and strategies that have everyone trying
to convince you that this is all more
than just gambling.
And hey,
maybe in some cases for some specific
users it is. It might be that there are
people who are really taking this
seriously and able to make a profit. But
that's not who the platforms are
marketing to.
>> What's the payout? So, 1,200 if I'm
right, bro?
>> And with such a heavy focus on the
gambling side of the business, there's
one aspect of all this that I find
really concerning.
If you haven't noticed, a lot of these
ads are specifically targeting younger
users. The minimum age for using
prediction markets is just 18, despite
the fact that some gambling laws push
this number up to 21. And this has led
to a pretty young user base for these
platforms. In fact, an estimated 24% of
Colchis users are under the age of 25,
which compares to 7% for DraftKings and
FanDuel. Which brings us to why these
platforms aren't just potentially risky,
they can also be outright dangerous.
Gambling is incredibly pervasive in the
United States. Online casinos and sports
betting is widely advertised in sports
games, podcasts, YouTube videos, and
with celebrity endorsements. Even the
White House has gotten in on the action
with Trump posting an ad for Stake,
which itself offers offshore casinos and
has been accused of facilitating
underage gambling. It demonstrates just
how much money and influence the
gambling industry has generated off of
its users.
It's also easier than ever to gamble
thanks to the gamblification of
everything, with even video games making
up part of the online gambling
ecosystem, and app development putting
the power of risking your life savings
in the palm of your hand. But gambling
addiction, which affects roughly 4% of
the US adult population, is an
incredibly dangerous disorder.
It can of course contribute to financial
ruin. A recent report by the Federal
Reserve Bank of New York found that
states with legalized mobile sports
gambling actually experience higher
consumer credit delinquencies, with
spillover effects even impacting
neighboring non-legal gambling states.
Gambling also increases the likelihood
of alcohol or drug abuse, is correlated
with domestic violence, and carries the
highest suicide rate among addiction
categories. And the issue is that young
adults, the very people these platforms
seem to be targeting, are the most
susceptible age demographic to the
disorder. A recent poll from Fairleigh
Dickinson noted that regarding men 30
and under who wager on sports, a group
that represents 25% of all men 30 and
under, a full 10% admitted to having a
gambling problem. And this all exists
even when companies follow state
gambling laws, when it's widely known
that gamblers on average lose money.
What happens when a platform or its avid
users convince people
that this is something different?
Financial nihilism is already a growing
trend where younger generations become
disillusioned with traditional financial
strategies and reject them in favor of
riskier gambles around crypto and the
like.
What happens if prediction markets are
themselves presented as the alternative
to investing in stocks for the long
term?
>> Stocks or bonds?
>> The weather.
>> Wait, you can trade on the weather?
>> Yeah, use Kalshi.
>> What happens when these markets manage
to financialize everything and have
everyone trading in their garage as
executives would like to have them? Will
all of this
still be good for society?
There's this idea in economics that
assigning a monetary value to something
can erode its social value. There's an
experiment carried out in Israel where
daycares implemented a fine on parents
who were late picking up their children,
only to see their late pickups double.
With researchers suspecting that parents
had crowded out their social obligation
with a monetary fee, thereby eliminating
the guilt they experienced from being a
burden to workers who had to stay late.
This is all highlighted in the book
Values by Canadian Prime Minister Mark
Carney, which yes, I waited this long to
share that given that politics, I knew
I'd lose some of you. But when we talk
about this idea of financializing
everything,
>> Our long-term vision is to financialize
everything and create a tradeable asset
out of any difference in opinion.
>> It's something worth considering.
Executives have put out this goal of
getting everyone to trade, not just
because it would make prediction markets
just
so much money, but because of the data
it would offer.
But with the odds being against the
average user, that just asks for
widespread losses. It is naturally a
negative-sum game when you account for
the fees charged by these platforms.
There's no productive use of these
investments, no project that might
generate additional cash flows, just a
general redistribution of wealth between
average people and those with better or
potentially insider information and
better infrastructure. Prediction
markets also inherently come with moral
hazard, the idea of incentives leading
to riskier behaviors.
Because if there's a payout to be had,
there's a cost or risk someone's willing
to take on to make it happen. We've
even, for example, had concerns raised
over so-called death contracts, with
both Polymarket and Kalshi having run
into criticism for markets around the
Iran war that involved the survival or
death of specific individuals. Now, can
prediction markets be useful? Certainly.
There's an endless list of hypotheticals
that executives will draw attention to
on how prediction markets can be used.
And yes, there is value in the
prediction data offered by these
markets.
Maybe less so for contracts on which
streamer will cry this month, but there
is evidence that wisdom of the crowds
works.
But it brings us to the ultimate
question.
Is it worth it? Is the cutting-edge
prediction data worth the financial
losses, the proliferation of gambling
addiction, and all the other
implications for users
when we talk about prediction markets?
Well,
it seems like that's what the courts
will be tasked with answering as we go
through the nearly 50 pending lawsuits,
some of which may very well make their
way up to the Supreme Court. And it's
worth noting that the CFTC is supposedly
putting together a framework to crack
down on insider trading. So, we'll have
to wait and see what that ultimately
looks like.
But, given this administration's track
record of loosening financial
regulations, pardoning people who have
explicitly worked against finance laws,
and entwining themselves in every latest
finance trend,
I wouldn't hold your breath. So, on that
note, we'll be taking wagers in the
comment section down below on which
topics you think the next Plain Bagel
video will be on. Yes, prediction
markets are technically still legal
where I live here in Canada, but I'm
sure we'll fix that sometime soon. So,
step right up, don't be shy. Any and all
wagers are welcomed. Leave a like for
your dealer if you'd like to leave a
tip, and don't sweat it.
It's not gambling if there's no casino.